<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sancheeta Kaushal</title>
    <description>Strong convictions precede great actions.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 15:32:56 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 15:32:56 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.5.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes for Building Microservices</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Preface:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Microservices are an approach to distributed systems that promote the use of finely grained services with their own lifecycles, which collaborate together. Because micro‐ services are primarily modeled around business domains, they avoid the problems of traditional tiered architectures.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It empowers autonomy, improves scaling.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Infra, automation and CD can help but if the fundamental system design isn’t good then there are limitations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Too many microservices is also a pain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microservices:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Domain-Driven Design helped us understand the importance of representing the real world in our code, and showed us better ways to model our systems.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CI has taught us how to treat every checkin as a candidate for release.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alistair Cockburn’s Hexagonal Architecture guided to layered arch where business layers could hide&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Netflix Antifragile Systems at Scale&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Microservices are small, autonomous services that work together.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Small focused on doing one thing well&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cohesion is the drive to have related code grouped together&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Single Responsibility Principle; Gather together those things that change for the same reason, and separate those things that change for different reasons.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How small is small ?
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Number of lines isn’t a great measure&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Something that can be rewritten in 2 weeks&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Small enough and no smaller
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;How well the service aligns to team structures&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;The benefits around interdependence increase and the downsides of having more and more parts start coming up&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Autonomous
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can you make a change to a service and deploy it by itself without changing anything else&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Key Benefits
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;SOA and distributed system&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tech heterogeneity to quickly absorb new tech
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Finding the right balance&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Netflix and Twitter, for example, mostly use the Java Virtual Machine (JVM) as a platform, as they have a very good understanding of the reliability and performance of that system&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Resilience
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Bulkhead: If one component of a system fails, but that failure doesn’t cascade, you can isolate the problem and the rest of the system can carry on working. Service boundary is the usual bulkhead&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Scaling
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;With microservices, scaling can be done in isolation and on-demand.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ease of Deployment
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2020 15:30:12 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/06/notes-for-building-microservices/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/06/notes-for-building-microservices/</guid>
        
        <category>Book</category>
        
        <category>Notes</category>
        
        <category>Tech</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes for Antifragile</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Prologue:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wind extinguishes a candle and energizes a fire.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some things benefit from shocks, they thrive and grow when exposed to voltality, randomness, disorder, stressors and love adeventure, risk and uncertainity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Antifragile is beyond resilience or robustness. Resilient resists shocks, antifragile thrives from shocks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Better to be dumb and antifragile than to be smart and fragile&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Love for certain types of errors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NonPrediction:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Easier to ask if something is fragile than to predict an event which can harm it&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Black Swan Problem is an unpredictable event that is beyond what is normally expected of a situation and has potentially severe consequences.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Extremely rare, have severe impact, insistence of being obvious in hindsight&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Detect antifragility through test of assymetry; Anything which has more upside than downside is antifragile; reverse is fragile&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deprivation of antifragility:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Depriving systems of randomness weekens them and kills them ultimately.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Top-down is fragalizing where as bottom up under right amount of strss thrives.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Those trying to help are often hurting the most. Eg. Overprotective parents&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Upside at the expense of others:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ethical rule - Thou shall not have antifragility at the cost of fragility of others&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Non risk takers with no accountability exert so much control in today’s world&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Definition of hero has gone a 360 degree change&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Antidote to Black Swan:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Events are retrospectively explainable and hence the illusion of predictabililty&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You get pseudo order when you seek order, when you embrace randomness you get order and control.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Complex systems have interdependencies which are hard to detect and have non-linear responses&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Manmade complex systems develop cascaded and chain of reactions which are really unpredictable&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 15:30:12 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/06/notes-for-Antifragile/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/06/notes-for-Antifragile/</guid>
        
        <category>Book</category>
        
        <category>Notes</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes for Designing Data-Intensive Applications</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Preface:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Today is the day of buzz words - NoSQL, Big Data, Web-scale, Sharding, Eventual consistency, ACID, CAP theorem, Cloud services, MapReduce, Real-time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Driving forces for development in data related systems
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Huge scale needs efficient processing of traffic and data&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Agility to test things quickly is really the key driver&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Prallelism is going to increase&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;IaaS has revolitionised the cloud and everyone has ability to excute things no matter which part of the world you are in&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An application is data intensive if data is primary challenge in terms of quantity, complexity &amp;amp; speed of change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scalable, available, resilient and curosity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building for scale that you don’t need is wasted effort and may lock you into an inflexible design. In effect, it is a form of premature optimization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foundations of data systems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapter 1:
	- Reliability
		- Software failures &amp;amp; bugs
	- Scalability
		- Load, Performance, Latency &amp;amp; Throughput
	- Maintainability
		- Operability, simplicity &amp;amp; evolvability
	- Applications need common functionality like databases, caches, search and filter, stream processing &amp;amp; batch processing&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2020 15:30:12 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/06/notes-for-designing-data-intensive-apps/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/06/notes-for-designing-data-intensive-apps/</guid>
        
        <category>Book</category>
        
        <category>Notes</category>
        
        <category>Tech</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes for Why We Sleep?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;To Sleep:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Insufficient sleep is the key reason for demolishing of immune system and increases the risk of diseases like Cancer, Alzheimers, Hearth Attack, Diabetes, Depression, Anxiety etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Too little sleep swells concentrations of hormone that makes us hungry and suppresses the one which signals food satisfaction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sleep deprivation not only relates to physical disorders but also to mental disorders.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lack of sleep can kill you outright
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Rare genetic disorder called progressive insomnia&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Drowsy driving leads atleast 1 death in America per hour&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We are so ignorant about sleep majorly because we haven’t been able to explain why we need it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is the only biological drive we haven’t been able to explain out of eating, drinking, reproducing and sleeping.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From an evolutionary perspective, given we can’t perform any activities and to top it we are more vulnerable to predators it is surprising why we sleep. If sleep doesn’t serve as absolutely vital function, then it is the biggest mistake the evolutionary process has made.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Benefits of sleep
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Health ensuring benefits&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mental functions of memory, learning, choices etc.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Recalibration of emotional brain circuits dealing with psychological challenges&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dream&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Strenghthens Immunity and Fights Inflammation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Regulates Appetite&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sleep as a diagnostic litmus test to understand type of dementia based on sleeping brainwaves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 15:30:12 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/06/notes-for-why-we-sleep/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/06/notes-for-why-we-sleep/</guid>
        
        <category>Book</category>
        
        <category>Notes</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes for Confirmation Bias</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Confirmation Bias&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Confirmation bias is our tendency to interpret facts or events in a way that confirms our pre-existing beliefs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Asking “What information would make you change your mind?”. If the answer to this is nothing then you know it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 15:30:12 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/05/notes-for-confirmation-bias/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/05/notes-for-confirmation-bias/</guid>
        
        <category>Biases</category>
        
        <category>Notes</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes for The Fearless Organisation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Preface:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Today’s world is all about knowledge workers and they need to innovate continuously.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For this to happen, they need to be able to share concerns, questions, mistakes and even half-formed ideas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Psychological safety is the key to performance in today’s world. Especially in the world of VUCA (Volatility, Uncertainty, Complexity, Ambiguity)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dynamic collaboration between teams is called Teaming. It’s the art of communicating and coordinating with people across boundaries of all kinds.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Project Aristotle by Google mentioned PS as the underpinning for all other criteria for the best performing teams. Others being Dependability, Structure and Clarity, Meaning &amp;amp; Impact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Underpinning:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unconscious Calculators:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Current Risk of speaking up vs Future benefit of solving the actual problem&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;High importance to interpersonal risks&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Worry about looking ignorant(don’t ask questions), incompetent(don’t accept mistakes) or disruptive(don’t make suggestions)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;85% of respondents in a study didn’t raise an issue with their boss even though they felt it as an important one&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Psychological safety an attribute of groups
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Speaking up facilitates open and authentic communication, focus on problems rather than people who made mistakes and open opportunities for improvement&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Microdynamics of face-saving by Goffman&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accidental Discovery
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Did better teams really make more mistakes? They don’t make more mistakes but they declare more mistakes.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Talk openly about mistakes and errors.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fear is not an effective motivator
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Productivity a phenomenon of the past. Knowledge work can’t be done the same way.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fear inhibits learning and collaboration.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;It consumes physiological resources diverting them from the parts that manage working memory to the amygdala and other fear response systems to deal with the situation.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;This blocks analytical thinking, creative insight and problem-solving.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Hierarchy is also a problem. We constantly assess our relative status wrt others subconsciously.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Psychological safety ensures that fear is no longer a problem. It’s a safe space. One focuses more on learning.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What PS is not ?
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It’s not about being nice all the time.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;It’s about candor and willingness to engage in productive disagrement so as to understand a different point of view.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It’s not about personality types.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;It refers to work climate and climate affects people with different personality traits.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It’s not same as trust
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Trust is individual, PS is a group phenomenon.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Trust is about whether you can rely on someone, PS is about temporally immediate experience.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Trust is about giving others a benefit of doubt, PS is about if you are given that benefit of doubt.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It’s not about lowering performance standards
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;We still need to hold people accountable. It’s just that they can except mistakes and we can work together on it.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;High PS, Low Standards: Comfort Zone&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Low PS, High Standards: Anxiety Zone&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Low PS, Low Standards: Apathy Zone&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;High PS, High Standards: Learning &amp;amp; Performing Zone&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chronbach’s Alpha for measuring inter-item reliability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Psychological Safety isn’t enough. We should hold high standards, inspire, coach and enable people by giving them apt and timely feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 15:30:12 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/05/notes-for-the-fearless-organization/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/05/notes-for-the-fearless-organization/</guid>
        
        <category>Book</category>
        
        <category>Notes</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes for an intro to psychology!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Week 2:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rene Descartes’s Philosophy
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Story of moving statue&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Concept of Soul/Dual Nature&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;James Mill Idea of Materialism&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Empiricism&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Luigi Galvini’s Frog experiment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paul Broca&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Broca’s Area in Brain related to production of speech&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wernicke’s Area in Brain related to comprehension of speech&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Human behaviour determined by natural laws and hence is a science&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clinical and Traditional Scientific Approach of Psychology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Psychology Before Freud
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Psychology born in Germany&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Hermann Von Helmholtz
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Speed with which neural tissue transfers info&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ernst Weber
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Sensory Stimuli&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Just noticable difference&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Weber fractions&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Psychophysics&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wilhelm Wundt
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Father of modern psychology&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Introspection&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Structualism
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Structure of Conscious Experience&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Darwin
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Why the features are the way they are ?&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Functionalism&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;William James
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Functionalism&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Function of psychology processes&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Psychology During Freud
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Sex and Agression least talked about things between men and women&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Psychic Conflict
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;It (Biological Drives with immediate Gratification)&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Super Ego (Perfect part of us)&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Ego (A state between It and Super Ego)&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Inner Conflict shaping our behaviour&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Deal with the cause of conflict&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Clinical Approach to Psychology&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Psychology After Freud
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Behaviourism&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;SR Psychology (Stimulus-Response)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Albert Experiment&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fear can be conditioned&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Other Fields of Psychology
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Experimental Psychology&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Cognitive Revolution at the time of computers&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Social Psychology at the time of political instability&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Individual Differences in terms of Intelligence, Personality&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Cross Cultural Psychology&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Positive Psychology like empathy, creativity&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Neuroscience
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Biological Revolution for understanding the brain eg. fMRI&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knowind the truth
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Knowing by Thinking&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Knowing by Senses&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 20:53:34 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/07/notes-for-intro-to-psycho/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/07/notes-for-intro-to-psycho/</guid>
        
        <category>Notes</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes for an intro to psychology!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Video 1:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Psychology comes from latin meaning study of soul&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The science of behavior and mental processes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Various schools of thought
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Structuralism
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Wilhelm Wundt&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Functionalism
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;William James&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Inspired by Charles Darwin&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Adaptive behaviours are conserved throughout the evolution&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Defined psychology as science of mental life&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Psychoanalysis
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Sigmond Freud&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Free Associate Technique&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Unconscious Motives&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Mental Disorders to be healed through talk therapy and self discovery&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Later descended to psychodynamic theory&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Behaviourism
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;B.F. Skinner&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video 2:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;False Intution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hindsight Bias (I knew it all along phenomenon)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Operationalizing the question&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Research Methods
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Scientific method
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Question and build a theory&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Make hypothesis and test your prediction&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Test with a replicable experiment&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Case studies can overgeneralizing&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Naturalistic observation
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Good at describing behaviour&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Limited in explaining it&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Surveys and interviews&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Experiments&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sampling Bias&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How behaviours corelate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;But corelation is not causation and hence cannot prove anything&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Experiments studying only one variable keeping others constant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Experimental and control group&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Placebo an inert substance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Double blind procedure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video 3:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everything psychological is biological&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neuron’s electrochemical nature
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Bipolar/Interneuron&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Unipolar/Sensory&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Multipolar/Motor&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pyramidal&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soma, Dendrites, Axon, Synapses and Myelin Sheath&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Multiple Sclerosis caused by damage to myelin sheath leading to lack of muscle control&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neurotransmitters
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Excitatory
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Norphinephrine&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Glutamate&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Inhibitory
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;GABA (Gamma Aminobutyric Axid)&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Seretonin&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Endorphins (Pain control and pleasure)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Acetylchlonin and Dopamine can behave as both&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Alzheimer’s patients experience deterioration of Acetylchlonin producing neurons&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Schizophrenia&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Endocrine System
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Hormones&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Attraction, Appetite and Aggression&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Take more time than neurotransmitters for reaction&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Adrenal Glands, Pencreas, Thyroid, Parathyroids, Ovaries, Pitutary Gland, Hypothalamus&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reuptake is a process of absorption of excess of neurotransmitter by the neuron that released them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video 4:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Phrenology is the study of shape and size of cranium&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Different parts of brain control specific behaviour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Function is localised&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brain and mind(memories, consciousness, behaviour, decisions)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How brain functions tie to the behaviour of mind&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CNS&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PNS&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Case of Phineas Gage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Old Brain
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Brain Stem&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Medulla&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pons&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Thalamus&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reticular Formation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cerebellum&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Limbic System
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Hypothalamus&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Amygdala&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Hippocampus&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Grey Matter in cerebrum
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Corpus Collosum&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Glial Cells&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lobes
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Frontal&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Parietal&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Occipital&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Temporal&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fissures&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cortex
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cerebral cortex&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Motor Cortex&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Somatosensory Cortex&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Association Areas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video 5:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prosopagnosia neurological disorder of face blindness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fusiform Gyrus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sensation vs Perception
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Bottom up process in which sensory organs receive and relay outside stimuli&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Top down way in which brain organizes and interpret information to put it into context&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Absolute threshold of sensation is the minimum stimulation needed to register a given stimulus 50% of the time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Signal Detection Theory is a model for predicting how and when a person will detect a weak stimuli partly based on context&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sensory Adaptation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Difference Threshold
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Weber’s Law is that we percieve differences on log scale and not linear scale&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wavelength and frequency determine hue&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Amplitude determine intensity or brightness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Photoreceptors
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Rods(Grayscale and Peripheral Vision) and Cones(Fine detail and color)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Theories of color vision
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Young Helmholtz Trichromatic Theory
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Dichromatic vs Trichromatic Vision&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Opponent Process Theory&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Feature Detector nerve cells&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Parallel Processing of Form, Motion, Depth and Color&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video 6:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Homunculus(little man) is sensory map of human body&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Short Waves have high frequency and high pitch&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Amplitude determines loudness measured in Decibels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Directional Stereophonic Hearing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ear Structure
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Outer Ear&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Middle Ear&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Inner Ear&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ear Drum&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ossicle Bones
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Stirrup&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Anvil&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Hammer&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cochlea&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Auditory Nerve&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Taste Buds
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Taste Pore&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Supporting Cell&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Gustatory Receptor Cell&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Umami Taste&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sensory Interaction&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Synesthesia is sensory activation of one sense when another sense is triggered.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Smell is Chemical Sense
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Olfactory Receptors&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Olfactory Bulb&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Primary Smell Cortex&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Odor Receptors&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Near our lymbic system - amygdala and hippocampus and hence related to emotional response&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Touching
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pressure&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Warmth&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cold&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pain&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kinesthesis is the way in which body senses it’s own movements and positioning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vestibular Sense monitors head’s position and balance
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Semicircular canals&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Vestibular Sac&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cochlea&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video 7:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Perception is the top-down way in which brain organises and interpret information and put it into context
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Make meaning out of our senses&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Duck vs Bunny&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Perceptual Set is the list of psychological factors that determine how we percieve the enviroment
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Context&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Culture&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Expectation&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Form Perception
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Figure Ground Relationship
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Organisation of visual field into objects that stand out from their surroundings&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Rules of grouping
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Orgainizing things by proximity&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Continuity&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Closure&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Depth Perception
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ability to see objects in 3D even when the retinal images are 2D&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Estimate distance and shape&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Binocular Cues and Retinal Disparity&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Monocular Cues
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Relative size and height&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Linear Perspective&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Texture Gradient&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Interposition&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Motion Perception
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Shrinking objects are retreating&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Enlarging objects are approaching&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Constancy
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ability to percieve objects even when stimulus changes slightly&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video 8:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consciousness
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Awareness of ourselves and our environment&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Stream of Consciousness&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What it means to be awake&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Waking&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dreaming&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tripping&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Sleeping&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cognitive neuroscience
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How brain activity is linked to our mental processes like thinking, perception, memory, language, pain etc&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Structural imaging&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Functional imaging
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Function is often localized in brain&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dual process model of consciousness
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Information processed simultaneously on conscious and non-conscious tracks&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;11 million bits of info per second&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Selective attention
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Way of focusing of our conscious awareness on a particular stimulus&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cocktail party effect&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inattentional Blindness
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Invisible gorilla&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Moonwalking bear&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Easy to miss something which we are not looking for&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Misdirection as experimental psychology&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change Blindness
 	- Psychological phenomenon in which we fail to notice changes in the environment
 	- Person Swap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video 9:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sleep is another state of consciousness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Periodic, natural, reversible and near total loss of consciousness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Different from hibernation, coma, anesthetic oblivion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reasons for sleeping
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Recuperation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Growth&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mental function&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Electroencephalograph(EEG)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;machine that measures brain’s electrical activity&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;REM Sleep stage
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Rapid Eye Movement&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Recurring sleep stage when vivid dreams occur&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sleep Stages
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;REM&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;NREM-1&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;NREM-2&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;NREM-3&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adrenal glands release cortisol awake harmone during day&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pineal gland release melatonin during night&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Before sleep alpha wave stage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hypnagogic Sensations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sleep Spindles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sleep deprivation leading to sleep disorders
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Insomnia has recurring problems in falling or staying asleep&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Narcolepsy uncontrollable sleep attacks
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Hypocretin&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Sleep Apnea can cause sleeper to temporarily stop breathing&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;REM Sleep Behaviour Disorder&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Night Terrors in NREM-3&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Sleep Walking&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Sleep Talking&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Nightmares in REM&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Post Traumatic Stress Disorder&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Oneirology
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Study of dreams&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Information Processing Theory&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Physiological Function Theory&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dreams are part of cognitive development
 	- Are Dreams side effects of REM sleep? Neural Activity Model&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video 10:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Animal Magnetism&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hypnosys as Altered State of Consciousness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hallucinations
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;A calm trance like state during which you have heightened concentration and focus with openess to suggestion&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Not a reliable way to recall deeply burried memories&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Hypnosis can’t make you act you against your will&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Social influence&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dissociation is a special dual processing state of split consciousness&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Selective inattention to pain&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In clinical hypnosys, people are asked to dissociate
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Highly hypnotizable&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adaptive Dissociative Capacity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drugs
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tolerance is the diminishing effect of a drug which happens with regular use and in order for them to be effective we start taking larger doses&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Neuroadaptation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Psychoactive Drugs are chemical substances which alter mood and perception
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Placebo Effect&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Depressants mellow slow bodily function and supress neural activity
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Alcohol&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Tranquilizers&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Opiates&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Disinhibitor impairs brain’s judgement areas, self awareness and self control&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Endorphins - Natural pain killing neurotransmitter&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Stimulants
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Speed up the bodily functions, enhance neural activity, self confidence and mood changes&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Caffine&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Nicotine&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Amphetamines&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Street Amphetamines&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Meth&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Ecstasy&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Cocaine&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Hallucinogens
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Also called psychedelics, they evoke sensory images and distort perceptions&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Plant&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Fungus&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Synthetic like LSD(Lysergic Acid Diethylamide)&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ways to hallucinate without drugs when neurological disturbances happen
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Seizures&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Brain injuries&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Sensory deprevation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fever&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Diseases&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Grief&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Depression&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video 11:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ivan Pavlov introduced behaviourism as a field psychology
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Science focused on observable behaviours and not unobservable internal mental processes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dog salivation experiment&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learning is the process of acquiring new and enduring information or behaviours through experience&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Associative Learning happens when a subject links certain events, behaviour and stimuli together in process of conditioning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acquisition and After conditioning phase&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Classic Conditioning is the type of learning where subject learns to link two or more stimuli and anticipate events&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learning can be studied through direct observation of behaviour
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Psychology about objective observable behaviour&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Operant Conditioning is a type of learning where behaviour is strengthened if followed by reinforcer or diminished if followed by punisher
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Shaping is an Operant Conditioning procedure in which reinforcers guide behaviour towards closer and closer approximations of the desired behavior
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Sucessive approximations&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Skinner box&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Air Crib&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Positive Reinforcement is a stimulus which when present after a response strengthens it&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Negative Reinforcement is a stimulus which when removed after a response strengthens it
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Negative Reinforcement is not punishment&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Primary Reinforcers is an innately biologically reinforcing stimulus&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Conditioned Reinforcers is a stimulus that gains it’s reinforcing power from association with primary reinforcer&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reinforcement schedules is a pattern that defines how often does a desired response will be reinforced&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Partial or intermittent reinforcement is a way in which we reinforce the behaviour only part of the time resulting in slower acquisition of response but much greater resistance to extinction than does continuous reinforcement&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Extinction&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cognitive processes also influence the way we learn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video 12:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Albert Bandura
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Bobo Beatdown&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Learning can occur through observing and immitating someone else’s behaviour&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Imitation is sincerest form of learning&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Observational Learning is learning by observing others&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Modelling is process of observing and imitating a specific behaviour&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Socio-Cognitive Learning&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Humans are more taste averse than sound/sight averse&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Birds are more sight averse&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not all associations are learnt equally
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Depends on species too as associations which help them survive and thrive are learnt with priority&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What we learn shapes our attitudes&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cognitions
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Thoughts, perspectives and expectations&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Latent Learning
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cognitive maps or mental representations of our surroundings&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learning
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Associating a response to a consequence&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Thinking&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neuroimaging&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reward systems work even when others are getting rewarded
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mirror neurons fire when performing some action or observing others to do so&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video 13:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HerpesViral Encephalitis wrecks the memory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Memory is the chain that connects past to present&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Personal Memories are stored differently&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Memory is learning persisted over time ie information that has been stored and can be recalled&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Memories accessed in 3 ways:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Recall is the measure of memory in which you access the already learned information&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Recognition is the measure of memory in which you identify items previously learned&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Relearning is the measure of memory in which you refreshing old information&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Memory formation
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;External Events lead to sensory memory&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Encoding to short term memory for under 30 seconds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Encoding to long term memory and further retrieval&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Working memory
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Conscious, active processing of auditory and visual-spatial information and info reterieved from long term memory&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Explicit Memory is the memory of facts and experiences one can consciously know and declare&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Implicit Memory is the retention of memory independent of conscious recollection&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Automatic processing
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Non-conscious encoding of incidental and well learned information&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Long term Memory
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Procedural Memory&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Episodic Memory&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mnemonics helps in memory aids especially those techniques that use vivid imagery and organisational devices
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Chunking is organising items into familiar managable units&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Shallow processing is encoding information based on auditory or visual levels eg. based on structure, appearance or sound of word&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Deep processing is encoding information based on the meaning associated with a word&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video 14:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lot of work to retrieve memories from the long term storage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Forget and Remember&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Retrieval Cues for backtracking memory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Priming is activating associations non-consciously
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Memoryless Memory&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Context Dependent Memory&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;State Dependent Memory&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Serial Positioning Effect
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Our tendency to best recall first and last items in a list&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Primacy Effect for first words which we rehearsed them more and were in long term memory&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Recency Effect for last words which remain in working memory&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We forget things in 3 ways:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;We fail to encode it&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;We fail to retrieve it
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Can happen because of interference of other memories in brain&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;We experience storage decay&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Proactive/Forward Acting Interference
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The disruptive effect of prior learning on the recall of new information&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Retroactive/Backward Acting Interference
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The disruptive effect of new learning on the recall of previous information&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Misinformation Effect
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Incorporating misleading information into one’s memory of an event&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Source Misattribution
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Forgetting or misrecalling the source of a memory&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video 15:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cognition
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Knowing&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Remembering&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Understanding&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Communicating&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Learning&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Concepts
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mental grouping of people, ideas, objects, events etc&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prototype
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mental image or pinnacle eg of a certain thing&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Problem Solving Techniques with plan of attack strategy
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Algorithms, Heuristics &amp;amp; Trial and Error&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Frontal lobes involved in attention of typical problem solving&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conformation Bias
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tendency to look for and favor evidence that confirms our ideas while avoiding or ignoring evidence to the contrary&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Belief Perseverance
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tendency to cling on to belief despite the proof to the contrary&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mental Set&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mentally available Memory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Availablity Heuristic is a mental shortcut relying on psychologically salient or easily imagined examples rather than actual odds or factual information&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Framing is how an issue is posed or presented&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 20:53:34 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/07/notes-for-psychology/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/07/notes-for-psychology/</guid>
        
        <category>Notes</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>An introduction to neuromarketing!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Week 1:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neuromarketing vs Consumer Neuroscience
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Commercial vs Academic&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Multidisciplinary ie Economics, Psychology and Neuroscience&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neuroscience vs Neurology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cognitive(Mental) or Affective(Emotional) Neuroscience&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Traditional Market Research is conscious behaviour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unconscious behaviour can be measured using Neuromarketing &amp;amp; Consumer Neuroscience&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stages
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Representation and Attention&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Predicted Value&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Experienced Value&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Remembered Value&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Learning of brand associations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Brand Memory&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brain Areas
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Gyrus, Sulcii and Fissures&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cerebellum engaged in motor control, emotional responses and cognitive functions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Lobes
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Occipital lobe engaged in visual input&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Temporal lobe engaged in object recognition, object and episodic memory and hearing and language&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Parietal lobe engaged in self awareness, spatial movement and dorsal stream function&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Frontal lobe engaged in working memory, preferences, decision making, motor behaviour&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dorsoletral Prefrontal Cortex is involved in working memory&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Anterior Singular Cortex&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Medial and Lateral Orbitofrontal Cortex&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pons&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mid Brain&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Basal Ganglia&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Thalamus&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Olfactory Bulb&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Insula&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Hippocampus&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Amygdala&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How we make choices ?
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Showing product made activations in nucleus aaccumbens/ventral striatum part of basal ganglia&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Showing price made activations in insula an emotional area in brain. Stronger the activate the less the chance of purchase&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;At the time of making choice, activations happened in medial prefrontal cortex&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conscious Gambling vs Unconscious Learning
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Nucleus Accumbens was engaged here&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fMRI
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;BOLD Signal ie Blood Oxygen-Level Dependent Signal&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Haemodynamic Response&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Regional Initial Dip then overshoot then undershoot and then stabalization&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Indirect measure of brain activation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Resting State task&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PET Scan
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dopamine, Seratonine and Glucose act in presence of radioactive ligand&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Week 2:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consumer choices driven by two main processes
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Unconscious quick and dirty valuation of immediate options&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Conscious experience of making a choice&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conscious Perception and Experience&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Episodic Memory - memory for conscious events&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sublimial Learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unconscious Vestibular Signals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Binocular Rivalry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inattention Blindness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Global Workspace Theory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conscious vs Unconscious Events&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Contexts and Goal Contexts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Waking consciousness is apparently needed for forward
spread of sensory activation to occur&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neural Dawinist Models&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Selective Attention&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unconscious Egocentric and Allocentric Cellular Maps&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Contralateral neglect&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Parietal cortex is involved in the first-person perspective&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attention and Consciousness
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Automatic attention&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Controlled attention&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Conscious Experience&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Selection process&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Attention is limited&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Bottom up vs top down attention&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Bottom up
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Automatically grab attention (contrast, density, movement, brightness, color, shape)&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Thalamus receives the signal projects to primary visual cortex&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Bottom up attention also called visual saliency&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Neurovision&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Top down
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Prefrontal and parietal part are involved&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Intentional Attention which is cognitively driven&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Consciousness is a state or an experience
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Purpose, challenging situations&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Unconscious during deep sleep
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Autopilot mode&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Brain consumes almost 20% of body energy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Brands can imbue value unconsciously and drive attention&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Much of actions taken as a consumer is unconscious&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Behaviour economics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incorrect assumptions with Intercept
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Asking the correct questions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Customer purchase was based on a conscious decision&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Customer’s capability to justify their purchase&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neurovision
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Visual Saliency meaning a heat map which is not so scattered&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fog map reverse of heat map&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consciousness is expensive in terms of energy needs amd autopilot behaviour makes sense&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Under stress or when we have less time to make decision, visual saliency has a lot to say about&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Week 3:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Five Sections of Brain
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Occipital: Visual processing&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Parietal: Attention, Self Awareness&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Temporal: Language, Memory and Visual Perception&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Frontal: Motor Control, Planning, Preference and Working Memory&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Insular: Emotions&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Other important brain structures
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Basal Ganglia: Putanum, Caudate Nucleus, Ventral Stratum&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Medial Temporal Lobe Structures - Hippocampus, Parietal Cortex, Amygdala&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cingulate Cortex: Anterior and Posterior&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Concepts of how brain works
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Redundancy: Function performed by two or more identical regions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Degeneracy: Function performed by two or more dissimilar regions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pluripotentiality: One structure can take on many roles&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Blind spot experiment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brain fills in meaning even when there is an incomplete visual scene&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dorsal and ventral stream of brain
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ventral stream from primary visual cortex to temporal cortex contain info about identity of objects&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dorsal stream is all about navigation&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Branding
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Odour&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Touch&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Sound&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sensory Neuromarketing
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Sensory Load chart&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Effect of scents on brand memory or brand recall&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sensory Load Chart&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;iMotions
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Eye tracking&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pupiliometry&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Distance to screens&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Blinks&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Attentional Blink&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;EEG&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Galvanic Skin Response&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;EMT&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Muscle Contractions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Heart Rate&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2018 15:53:34 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/06/notes-for-neuromarketing/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/06/notes-for-neuromarketing/</guid>
        
        <category>Notes</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Visual Perception and the Brain!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Week 1:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can’t explain perception which is the end result of vision&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Perception is what we are aware of&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Physical Measurements are objective&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Psychophysical Measurements are subjective&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Perception of Luminacnce
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Relative Lightness&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Measured with phonometer&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spectrophotometer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Geometry
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Angle Perception&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Motion Perception&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Direction Perception&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Perception is at odds with reality&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inverse Optics Problem ie no way of getting back the exact composition of retinal stimulus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inverse problems makes source of any image uncertain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Source of Illumination&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3D object surfaces&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Atmosphere&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Retinal Stimulus is compilation of
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Illumination&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reflectance&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Transmittance is the alteration of light by the atmosphere&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visual Stimuli&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Light and Electromagnetic Radiation
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Human visual system from 400 nm to 700 nm&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To lower size range, the energy tends to damange cells&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To greater size range, the energy tends to be present as heat&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making an image
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;There is no image out there in the world just the mess of photons&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cornea orders out this photonic flux&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eye
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cornea
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Refractive Abilities&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Refrative index is greater than air&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Lens is attached by zonule fibres
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Involved in fine bending of light&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cilliary muscles contract or relax to change the shape of lens&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Vitreous Humor&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Optic Disk (Papilla)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Macula Lutea&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ophtalmic Arteries and Veins&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eye Tracking
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Saccadic Eye movements&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Retina
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Interface between neural and non-neural parts of eye&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fovea&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pigment Epithelium&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Photoreceptor Layer
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Rods and Cones&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ganglion Cells are output layer cells&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Bipolar Cells responsible for high resolution&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Amarcrine Cells responsible for capturing horizontal information&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Light -&amp;gt; To Optic Nerve -&amp;gt; Ganglion Cell -&amp;gt; Amacrine Cell -&amp;gt; Bipolar Cell -&amp;gt; Horizontal Cell -&amp;gt; Rods -&amp;gt; Cones -&amp;gt; Photoreceptors -&amp;gt; Pigment Eplithelium&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Photo receptors have a high metabolic rate and discs on Pigment epithelium are turned over at high rate and are being degraded and need to be removed on an ongoing basis to function properly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Distribution of rods and cones
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cones are concentated near and at the center of fovea&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Rods are concentrated near the periphery of retina&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cone function is one to one and rod function is many to one&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At absolute thrshold of vision rods operate and in bright sunlight cones operate and in moonlight both operate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Primary Visual Pathway
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Eye&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Thalamus&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Primary visual cortex&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Superior Colliculus
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Concerened with eye and head movements&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Autonomic Pathway
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pupilary Light Reflex
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Concerned with pupil dilation&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Optic Chaism
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Place where visual information crossing happens&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tail flip effect
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Information flipping and going on opposite side of brain&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thalamus
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Way station responsible for sensory organs&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Lateral Geniculate Nucleus responsible for vision
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;4 parvo-cellular layers concerned with full view vision, precision and color&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;2 magno-cellular layers concerned with grosser change in the image or movement&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Retinotopy
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Neighbour relationship of pixels of image&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ganglion Cells of retina
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;parvo-ganglion cells&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;magno-ganglion cells&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PVC in occipital lobe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Peak are gyri and valleys are sulci in the brain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Optic Radiation are the optic fibres going from the the thalamus to Visual Cortex and vice versa&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Striate Cortex&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 23 Mar 2018 15:53:34 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/03/notes-for-visual-perception-and-the-brain/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/03/notes-for-visual-perception-and-the-brain/</guid>
        
        <category>Notes</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
